RG 130, Order of the Founders and Patriots of America, Connecticut Society
Connecticut State Library
Order of the Founders and Patriots of America, Connecticut Society records
1896-1914
Connecticut State Library
Order of the Founders and Patriots of America. Connecticut Society
9 cubic feet
The Order of the Founders and Patriots of America was incorporated in New York on March 18, 1896. The terms of eligibility require that every member must be descended in the male line of father or mother, from an ancestor who settled in one of the original thirteen colonies within fifty years from the settlement of Jamestown, VA, May 13, 1607.
RG130
1915-022
Historical Note
The Order of the Founders and Patriots of America was incorporated in New York on March 18, 1896. The motive leading to its formation was the desire to meet certain requirements not met by existing organizations where membership did not indicate that the immediate ancestors during the War for Independence be loyal to the American cause. Its insignia is a badge of double honor - "honor of descent from those brave and hardy pioneers who subdued the primeval wilderness and first planted within the limits of the original colonies the civilization which now leads the world, and honor of descent from those who, in patriotism and devotion and love of liberty, founded the first republic in the western hemisphere...."1
The terms of eligibility require that every member must be descended in the male line of father or mother, from an ancestor who settled in one of the original thirteen colonies within fifty years from the settlement of Jamestown, VA, May 13, 1607. An additional requirement stipulated that the member be descended through the same line from a patriot in the Revolutionary War, but not of necessity through those who rendered military service.
The Connecticut members set up their own Society on May 9, 1896, and the organization has continued to meet regularly, publish various items and engage in other activities.
Endnotes
1The Order of the Founders and Patriots of America. Register: 1926. p. 9.
Scope and Content
The records include correspondence, minutes of meetings, publications, a scrapbook, and treasurer’s records.
Related Material
Order of the Founders and Patriots of America. Connecticut Society
Design and description of the seal of the Connecticut Society of the Order of the Founders and Patriots of America, 1607-1776, 1 document, manuscript
Address entitled "The Founders of Connecticut and their descendants in the Wars of the Country" with notation that the paper was probably written by Professor Charles H. Smith of Yale about 1907, 11 pages, typescript.
[CSL call number StLib Archives 369.125Conn C76].
Index Terms
Organizations:
Order of the Founders and Patriots of America. Connecticut Society
Subjects:
Order of the Founders and Patriots of America. Connecticut Society -- Records and correspondence; Connecticut -- Societies, etc
Document Types:
Correspondence; Scrapbooks; Minutes; Publications; Financial records
Restrictions on Access
See the policy.
Provenance
The records were received from the Society in 1915, 1918, 1922, and 1942, and by purchase from Mrs. Edwards in 1941.
Container List
- Records, 1896-1914
  - Minutes, 1896-1914; 1 volume (Box 1)
  - "Miscellaneous records", 1897-1904; 1 envelope (Box 1)
    Secretary's book (with drafts of minutes, lists of members, etc.), Treasurer's reports, bills, receipts, etc.
  - Publications, 1897-1912
    Bound sets of the published papers.
    - Connecticut Society, no. 1-11, 1900-1911; 1 volume (Box 1)
    - New York Society, no. 1-15, 1897-1906; 1 volume (Box 2)
    - New York Society, no. 16-32, 1906-1912; 1 volume (Box 2)
  - Historian's scrapbook, 1896-1914 (Box 3)
    Scrapbook, with clippings on Society activities and members, correspondence and other materials.
  - Letterbox file, 1904-1906; 1 volume (Box Item 4)
    Correspondence of Walter Collyer Faxon, Governor of the Connectictut Society, relating to Society activities.
  - Photographs, 4 large albums + 2 envelopes (Box Unnumbered items)
    Contains photographs of many of the first 200 members of the Connecticut Society and lease photographs in envelope and holder.